<events>
  <events24Adds0>The reserve will be equal to 100</events24Adds0>


  <events44Desc0>@The figure of Joseph Stalin is one of the most controversial not only in Russian history but also in world history. For some, he is a tyrant and a criminal who killed millions of people for the sake of personal power. For others, he is the "father of nations" who led the country in difficult times, modernized it, which allowed it to survive and win the world war. After the death of the leader, his successors from among his closest associates began to carry out "de-Stalinization". At the 20th Congress of the CPSU, Nikita Khrushchev exposed the "cult of Stalin's personality". In 1957, Stalin's old associates (the so-called "anti-party group") attempted to remove Khrushchev, which, however, failed, and after some time the conspirators were sent into retirement and expelled from the party. At the 22nd Congress, criticism of Stalin and the anti-party group only intensified. |@After Khrushchev's resignation, the active anti-Stalin campaign was curtailed, and the new leadership moved to more restrained and positively neutral assessments of Stalin's personality and rule. However, over the years the tendency for "political rehabilitation" of Stalin grew. |@It reached its apogee during the rule of Konstantin Chernenko. Thus, Vyacheslav Molotov, who had been expelled from there in 1961 with the wording "for participation in mass repressions against thousands of honest Soviet communists", was reinstated in the ranks of the CPSU. The Central Committee began to receive petitions for the rehabilitation of other members of the "anti-party group" - Georgy Malenkov and Lazar Kaganovich, but they were never approved. By May 9, 1985, Chernenko was preparing a special resolution reviewing Stalin's activities and personality, which, however, he did not manage to complete. |@I think now is the best time to end this issue.</events44Desc0>
  <events44Desc1>@The figure of Joseph Stalin is one of the most controversial not only in Russian history but also in world history. For some, he is a tyrant and a criminal who killed millions of people for the sake of personal power. For others, he is the "father of nations" who led the country in difficult times, modernized it, which allowed it to survive and win the world war. After the death of the leader, his successors from among his closest associates began to carry out "de-Stalinization". At the 20th Congress of the CPSU, Nikita Khrushchev exposed the "cult of Stalin's personality". In 1957, Stalin's old associates (the so-called "anti-party group") attempted to remove Khrushchev, which, however, failed, and after some time the conspirators were sent into retirement and expelled from the party. At the 22nd Congress, criticism of Stalin and the anti-party group only intensified.|@After Khrushchev's resignation, the active anti-Stalin campaign was curtailed, and the new leadership moved to more restrained and positively neutral assessments of his personality and rule.|@In recent years, a tendency has emerged to revise the assessment of Stalin's activities. In 1984, Vyacheslav Molotov was reinstated in the party, after which the Central Committee began to receive requests for the rehabilitation of other members of the "anti-party group" - Georgy Malenkov and Lazar Kaganovich.|@I think now is the best time to put an end to this issue.</events44Desc1>
  <events44Answer0>Начать полное восстановление образа Сталина</events44Answer0>
  <events44Answer1var1>Stalin did 70% good and 30% bad</events44Answer1var1>
  <events44Answer1var0>Let's continue the line of comrade Chernenko</events44Answer1var0>
  <events44Answer2>Rehabilitate Stalin as the great leader of Russia</events44Answer2>
  <events44Answer3>Organize a new anti-Stalin campaign</events44Answer3>
  <events44Answer4>Stalin is just a puppet of the Zionists in the Soviet leadership</events44Answer4>
  <events44Answer5>Do nothing</events44Answer5>
  <events44Result0>@All official Soviet newspapers published a resolution "On the correction of the subjective approach and excesses that occurred in the second half of the 1950s and early 1960s in assessing the activities of I. V. Stalin and his closest associates", in which Khrushchev was blamed for deviating from the principles of collective management and conducting an "anti-Stalin campaign" in order to strengthen his own power. Stalin once again, without any reservations, appeared in all textbooks as a great Soviet leader and a loyal Leninist who managed to modernize the country in the shortest possible time and win the Great Patriotic War. All accusations of creating a personality cult were dismissed with reference to one of the quotes of the writer Mikhail Sholokhov: "There was a cult, but there was also a personality!" The city of Volgograd was given back its former name – Stalingrad.|@The repressions of 1937–1938 were deemed “necessary” because they “made it possible to avoid the emergence of a fifth column during the war.”</events44Result0>
  <events44Result1>@All official Soviet newspapers published the resolution "On the correction of the subjective approach and excesses that occurred in the second half of the 1950s and early 1960s in assessing the activities of I. V. Stalin and his closest associates." |@A slow, gradual political rehabilitation of the entire anti-party group began, and Khrushchev was blamed for departing from the principles of collective management. Stalin was recognized as 70% good and 30% bad, as Mao had once determined. |@The modernization of the country and the victory in the Great Patriotic War were noted as unconditional positive aspects of Stalin's rule. The formation of a personality cult and the departure from collective leadership were criticized. The "costs" during the implementation of the collectivization policy were blamed on the "excesses" of local authorities, who violated the general line of the party. Responsibility for the repressions was placed on the punished Yagoda and Yezhov, while Tukhachevsky and Timoshenko were found guilty of the first military failures of 1941.</events44Result1>
  <events44Result2>@All official Soviet newspapers published a resolution "On the correction of the subjective approach and excesses that occurred in the second half of the 1950s and early 1960s in assessing the activities of I. V. Stalin and his inner circle." It proclaimed Stalin a "great statesman" who managed to "strengthen the power and military glory of Russia, save the country from occupation and total destruction." Stalin was able to abandon "anti-Russian internationalism" and the policy of indigenization and finally create a "people's empire" headed by a "wise leader." The repressions were deemed "insufficient" because, despite the fact that the war had been won, "a significant portion of national traitors joined the Vlasovites, Banderites and other fascist organizations," and soon "Stalin's too soft attitude toward his opponents" became the cause of his death "as a result of a Trotskyist conspiracy" organized by his entourage in the persons of Khrushchev, Malenkov, Bulganin and Beria. |@Now Russia's history has its own "Red Monarch"...</events44Result2>
  <events44Result3>@The third round of de-Stalinization (following the two Khrushchev ones) began. Real battles for the "rethinking of the past" unfolded on the cultural front.|@The film "Repentance" by Georgian director Tengiz Abuladze was released in wide release, where the main character was the corpse of an official responsible for the repressions against his own people, which the heroes of the film dug out of the ground again and again, not allowing the terrible past to quietly rest in the grave.|@The fiction books about terror and Stalinism made a huge impression on society. Previously banned works were published, such as Requiem by Anna Akhmatova, Voronezh Notebooks by Osip Mandelstam, Doctor Zhivago by Boris Pasternak, Kolyma Tales by Varlam Shalamov, Children of the Arbat by Anatoly Rybakov, Life and Fate by Vasily Grossman, Sofia Petrovna by Lidiya Chukovskaya, The Steep Route by Evgenia Ginzburg, and The Faculty of Unnecessary Things by Yuri Dombrovsky. |@In addition to fiction, historical science is also being put into circulation. Previously inaccessible archives are being opened, dozens of collections of historians' discussions on Stalin and Stalinism are being published, and works by Western Sovietologists are being published. |@State policy has also changed. The rehabilitation of scientists, party members, and other victims of political repression convicted under Stalin has begun. The government adopted the decree "On the construction of a monument to the victims of lawlessness and repression" and the laws "On the rehabilitation of repressed peoples" and "On the rehabilitation of victims of political repression". |@Rethinking the past will not allow our country to return to tyranny... At least we hope so...</events44Result3>
  <events61Desc>@For the last half century, the name of Leon Trotsky has been used in our country together with such derogatory words as "opportunist", "Menshevik", "fascist counter-revolutionary" and "traitor Judas". Few people remember who Trotsky really was and why he became so hated in the Soviet Union, although he played an important role in the history of the Russian revolution. Trotsky's figure remains a mystery to our citizens, although thousands of pages of his works and publications about him are still in libraries, albeit in restricted access.|@It is time to appeal to the court of historical justice - we can no longer remain silent about such a significant figure, a revolutionary, one of the organizers of the October Revolution and the founder of the Red Army, who fell victim to the party struggle and was expelled from the country, but did not abandon political activity and was eventually killed by the NKVD agent Ramon Mercader on Stalin's orders.|@Socialist heroes must not be forgotten!</events61Desc>
  <events61Answer0>Completely rehabilitate Trotsky</events61Answer0>
  <events61Answer1>Partially rehabilitate the activities and role of Trotsky</events61Answer1>
  <events61Answer2>Legal rehabilitation is enough</events61Answer2>
  <events61Answer3>Postpone the decision</events61Answer3>
  <events61Result0>@Along with the rehabilitation of such a great communist revolutionary as Leon Trotsky, a month dedicated to him also began. An agreement was reached with the leadership of Mexico and the United States on the return of all of Trotsky's archives to {0}, as well as on the establishment of a house-museum in Coyoacan financed by the Government {0}. All decisions of the congresses of the 1930s that criticized him were cancelled, and the publication of Trotsky's works and the "Bulletin of the Opposition" was resumed. After that, many settlements, streets, educational institutions, collective farms, etc. were renamed in honour of Trotsky, and monuments began to be erected in his honour. At the same time, Stalin's personality began to be spoken of even more negatively, given his role in Trotsky's fate. The formation of a cult of Trotsky's personality began in the country.</events61Result0>
  <events61Result1>@Following a heated debate, the following assessment of Leon Trotsky's activities and personality was given: 70% merits and achievements, and 30% mistakes. Thus, his merits in the victory of the October Revolution, the formation of the Red Army, and the defeat of the White Guards and interventionists were recognized, but his factional and émigré activities were still assessed negatively. His early works and a three-volume classic biography of Trotsky by the Polish-British historian Isaac Deutscher were published. Trotsky's later works were published in a small print run for libraries with extensive editorial commentary. |@In general, this assessment suits everyone or at least many for whom it is important and necessary. Nevertheless, despite the criticism, Trotsky still returned to the "pantheon of leaders of the revolution."</events61Result1>
  <events61Result2>@Today, the Prosecutor's Office {0} rehabilitated L. D. Trotsky (Bronstein) due to the absence of corpus delicti. The resolution of the Special Conference of the OGPU Collegium of the USSR of 31.12.1927 on expulsion to Siberia for 3 years, as well as the decision of the Politburo of the Central Committee of the All-Union Communist Party of Bolsheviks of 10.01.1929 and the resolution of the Presidium of the Central Executive Committee of the USSR of 20.02.1932 on expulsion from the USSR with deprivation of citizenship and prohibition of entry into the USSR, were recognized as illegal and invalid.</events61Result2>
  <events61Result3>@We'll come back to this issue later</events61Result3>
  <events62Desc>@Russia has had no luck with reformers. All great reforms either failed or were excessively cruel in their implementation. The aura of such a "failed reformer" and "Russia's last hope" was formed around the personality of Pyotr Arkadyevich Stolypin. |@A nobleman by birth, Stolypin made a brilliant career in a few years - from the governor of a small town on the outskirts of the Empire to the head of the government. His stunning rise was facilitated by the First Russian Revolution. Having proven himself to be a successful "pacifier of the revolution", Stolypin received the post of Minister of Internal Affairs, and after the dissolution of the First State Duma, he headed the government. |@In this post, he successfully "calms" the country after several years of unrest and begins the most large-scale reform in the last 50 years, which, according to his plan, should "make an American farmer out of a Russian peasant." However, he was unable to fully implement his ideas. In September 1911, Stolypin was shot by a terrorist in the Kyiv Opera House. |@As historians show, Stolypin's attempts to destroy the community and solve the problem of "agrarian resettlement" through a resettlement policy to the east of the country were a failure. Some see the reasons for the failure of the reform in the war that had begun, others - in the revolution. And, in this regard, Stolypin's own words seemed somewhat prophetic: "Give the State twenty years of peace, internal and external, and you will not recognize today's Russia!" Russia did not see peace, but it became unrecognizable. |@Now, more than ever, it is important for us to understand - who was Stolypin? A great reformer who could have saved Russia from a bloody war and revolution? Or a great national figure who sought to modernize the country and make Russia the most influential world power, but failed due to "internal enemies"? Or was the domestic historiography of the last decades right, branding him as a “hangman” who drowned the Russian revolution in blood in the interests of the landowners?</events62Desc>
  <events62Answer0>Stolypin - the great reformer</events62Answer0>
  <events62Answer1>Stolypin – great national figure</events62Answer1>
  <events62Answer2>Let's leave everything as is</events62Answer2>
  <events62Result0>@Unexpectedly for everyone, {1} took part in one of the largest historical conferences devoted to the study of capitalist Russia, in his speech he stood up for his pre-revolutionary predecessor Pyotr Stolypin.|@The head of the country was prompted to take a historical excursion by one of the conference participants, who called Stolypin's reforms a failure and suggested that the prime minister-reformer was not the kind of person "worth looking up to."@|{2} acknowledged that during Stolypin's years in office, the military field courts created by his government sentenced 2.5 thousand people to death. "There is nothing good about this, of course," said the leader of {0}, but he called for such actions to be considered in a historical context.|@He also recalled that at that time 18 thousand russians suffered at the hands of terrorists. "Stolypin believed that harsh measures against people who were destabilizing the state were justified at that time," said the head of government. "I hope that descendants will distinguish the blood on the hands of a doctor from the blood on the hands of an executioner," {2} quoted Stolypin as saying.|@The leader of the state also gave his assessment of Stolypin's reforms: "Basically, thanks to the reforms, Russia has taken first place in the world in terms of economic growth." He also named the fact that the butter produced in Siberia by peasant settlers brought in more money to the treasury than the sale of gold as a clear indicator of the success of Stolypin's reforms.|@In conclusion, {2} noted that Stolypin's reforms represent "taking into account the interests of the state and society, based not on the dictate of power, but on encouragement, incentives, and interaction."|@Many historians and politicians perceived the speech of the leader of the state as a "call to action" and immediately began to praise the former "hangman."</events62Result0>
  <events62Result1>@Unexpectedly for everyone, {1} took part in one of the largest historical conferences devoted to the study of capitalist Russia, in his speech he stood up for his pre-revolutionary predecessor Pyotr Stolypin.|@The head of the country was prompted to take a historical excursion by one of the conference participants, who called Stolypin's reforms a failure and suggested that the prime minister-reformer was not the kind of person "worth focusing on".@|"Pyotr Arkadyevich Stolypin is an outstanding statesman of the 20th century on the scale of different centuries of Russia, whose participation in the affairs of governing the country delayed the death of the monarchy," the head of state began his speech. According to him, "the figure of Stolypin is the crossroads of all the burdens of Russia." "The duty of a statesman ordered him, ruthlessly suppressing unrest, to direct moral force to the renewal of the country. He accepted state life in disarray and chaos - and pulled it out creatively. He put everything into his state policy, he led it with his heart, mind and life." Summing up, {2} noted that Stolypin and his policy "could have saved Russia from the troubles of war and revolution," but "internal enemies" and "the stubbornness of the last tsar" prevented this. |@Many historians and politicians perceived the speech of the leader of the state as a "call to action" and immediately began to praise the former "hangman." However, not everyone liked the speech of the leader {0}. Some noted that the entire speech of the head of state "was replete with literary qualities," and one historian even called this assessment "a panegyric to the hangman of the Russian people."</events62Result1>
  <events62Result2>@Stolypin is a hangman and tormentor of workers! At least until we say otherwise!</events62Result2>
  <events63Answer4>Наложить санкции на Иран всем {0}</events63Answer4>
  <events63Result4>@{0} and all countries {1} have joined the sanctions against Iran, which include a ban on international financial institutions issuing loans to Iran, and on all countries selling weapons and any assistance to Iran. All trade between {1} and Iran has also been completely banned.</events63Result4>
  <events68Title>Sakalauskas case</events68Title>
  <events68Desc>@A week ago, a mail and baggage train arrived at the far platform of the Moscow railway station, which included a special car for transporting convicts. In addition to the prisoners, the car contained eight military personnel providing security and one civilian. Upon arrival, no one left the car. During the inspection of the car, eight corpses were found. One of the escorts, Lithuanian private Arturas Sakalauskas, was not there. Five pistols and five spare magazines were missing from the gun cabinet. All suspicion fell on Sakalauskas. After some time, he was found on a bus. As it turned out, in recent days he had been aimlessly traveling around the city on public transport. After his arrest, Sakalauskas gave extensive testimony, describing in detail the abuse, the attempted rape, and the murders themselves. During the investigation, the detainee began to develop reactive psychosis.@|This unpleasant story illustrates a significant problem that is very common in our army, namely hazing - a hierarchy in relationships among servicemen, associated with the length of service. Something must be done to prevent such a tragedy from happening again.</events68Desc>
  <events68Answer0>Сократить длительность призыва</events68Answer0>
  <events68Answer1>Make military service more transparent</events68Answer1>
  <events68Answer2>Strengthen criminal prosecution of hazing in the army</events68Answer2>
  <events68Answer3>Under this pretext, launch a critique of the army leadership</events68Answer3>
  <events68Answer4>Recognize Sakalauskas as mentally ill and send him for compulsory treatment</events68Answer4>
  <events68Answer5>Keep silent about what happened</events68Answer5>
  <events68Result0>@The tragedy that occurred led to growing public indignation at the phenomenon of "hazing" in the army. Against this background, the Government announced a reduction in the conscription period, which should shake the established hierarchical relations among military personnel. Despite the fact that the reduction in the conscription period was welcomed by military-liable citizens, the generals remained dissatisfied with the reduction in the army's combat readiness and the undermining of discipline.</events68Result0>
  <events68Result1>@Military commissariats responsible for conscription received huge state investments. Thanks to modern computers, it was possible to overcome bureaucratic chaos and red tape in military command bodies, which will make the "sorting" of conscripts into military units more flexible and transparent. According to forecasts, this should undermine the existing hierarchical relations among military personnel, at least to some extent.</events68Result1>
  <events68Result2>@The Criminal Code was amended to include the article on "violation of statutory rules of relations between military personnel in the absence of subordination relations between them." The minimum term for "hazing" was increased from two years to eight, and the maximum from twelve to twenty-five. It is difficult to say how this change will affect relations between military personnel, since the army is not very fond of "airing dirty linen in public."</events68Result2>
  <events68Result3>@The country's largest newspapers published articles detailing the "Sakalauskas case." All blame for the tragedy is placed on the army leadership, which allowed the "moral character of the army to deteriorate." This event and its subsequent discussion in the media caused a public outcry and led to an increase in the number of "draft dodgers." However, despite all this, an important topic for society was raised, which had previously been ignored. Perhaps the impact of the media will continue to draw attention to this problem.</events68Result3>
  <events68Result4>@Based on the results of a medical examination, the arrested Sakalauskas was declared insane and was sent for treatment at a psychiatric hospital. The conclusion stated that he had been diagnosed with a "continuously progressing chronic mental illness." The real cause of the tragedy was "hushed up" and pushed out of public consciousness, which was certainly appreciated by the army leadership.</events68Result4>
  <events68Result5var0>@The tragic events at the Moscow railway station were successfully covered up. The defendant Sakalausas himself was sentenced to several years for mass murder. The generals were pleased that you decided not to undermine the image of our army.</events68Result5var0>
  <events68Result5var1>@We failed to hide the secret of the mass murder from the media. Information about the tragedy leaked into the newspapers and immediately became a sensation. A public discussion about "hazing" in the army unfolded throughout the country, calls appeared to abolish compulsory military service, and the number of "draft dodgers" increased many times over.</events68Result5var1>
